<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
		xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
        xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
         				http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd">

	<info>
		<title>bwReg</title>
		<subtitle>Installation, Configuration &amp; Development</subtitle>
		<author>
			<personname>
				<firstname>Michael</firstname>
				<surname>Simon</surname>
			</personname>
		</author>
		<author>
			<personname>
				<firstname>Jens</firstname>
				<surname>Köhler</surname>
			</personname>
		</author>
		<author>
			<personname>
				<firstname>Saher</firstname>
				<surname>Semaan</surname>
			</personname>
		</author>
	</info>

	<preface>
		<title>Foreword</title>
		<para>
			This application was first developed as part of the bwIdm Project.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Thanks</title>
			<para>
				Thanks go to the bwIdm Project Members, Ministerium, ...
			</para>
			<para>
				OpenSAML library, Jonathan Tellier (PAOS classes), Apache Directory Team, ...
			</para>
			<para>
				Early adopters: Saher Semaan, Nomi Meixner, Stefan Kombrink, Tobias Kienzle, ...
			</para>
		</section> 
	</preface>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Requirements</title>
		<section>
			<title>Application Server</title>
			<para>
				The bwReg application is a JEE Application using the JEE6 standard. In order to 
				run it needs a JEE6 capable application server. Some features (cluster singleton) are using special API
				from the JBoss Application Server in Version 7.2.0 (i.e. JBoss EAP 6.1.0). There is 
				a possibility that the application will also run with other application servers, but 
				this has not been tested yet. The cluster singleton feature will not run in 
				an alternate environment, until there is a standard compliant way of having a singleton
				cluster-wide. 
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Database</title>
			<para>
				As a database for the application, any database which is compliant to the JPA provider used
				by the application server. In case of JBoss Application Server Hibernate is used as a JPA
				provider, which support a variety of databases. Until now, the application has been successfully tested
				with PostgreSQL and Microsoft SQLServer. 
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Installation</title>
		<section>
			<title>JBoss Application Server</title>
			<para>
				The installation of the application server should be done according to your system requirements 
				and the instructions manual of the product. 
				The webregistration has been tested and deployed in an standalone and domain mode environment and
				works in a cluster. The "standalone-full-ha" profile is needed for the application. 
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Update</title>
		<para>
			In order to update the application, you simply have to undeploy the old version, and deploy
			the new version. Most of the database schema updates are handled automatically via 
			Hibernate at the moment. This behavior may change in the future. Sometimes it is not 
			possible to update the schema because of database constraints. In this case the version is 
			listed below.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Update to version 1.4.0</title>
			<para>
				User reconciliation is not done automatically anymore. It is now event driven.
				To get the previous behavior back, follow the instructions in the section
				<command linkend="user_reconciliation">User Reconciliation</command>.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Update to version 2.3.0</title>
			<para>
				There are some changes in the datamodel from version 1 to version 2. To reflect these changes
				the table "group_store" has to be extended with the column "DTYPE". For existing entries the DTYPE has
				to be set to "HomeOrgGroupEntity". The column has to be "NOT NULL". With the application server stopped
				the SQL commands for MS SQL are for example:
			</para>
			<programlisting language="sql">
ALTER TABLE group_store ADD DTYPE varchar(31);
UPDATE group_store SET "DTYPE" = 'HomeOrgGroupEntity';
ALTER TABLE group_store ALTER COLUMN DTYPE varchar(31) NOT NULL;
			</programlisting>
			<para>
				The application behaves differently regarding groups now. It should be possible to have same group names and
				gidNumbers for different groups, depending on the service, the group is connected with. To make this 
				possible, you have to remove all unique constraints (if set) on "gid_number" and "group_name" in the table
				"group_store".
			</para>
			<para>
				After starting the application server again, with the new version ear, some new tables will be created.
				The tables "user_event" and "service_event" are no longer used. The data contained in there is now 
				processed from the table "event_table". To migrate the existing data, you could use the following SQL
				statements (MS SQL specific):
			</para>
			<programlisting language="sql">
INSERT INTO event_table (DTYPE, id, created_at, updated_at, [version], eventType, jobClass_id) 
	SELECT 'UserEventEntity', id, created_at, updated_at, [version], eventType, jobClass_id
		FROM user_event;

INSERT INTO event_table (DTYPE, id, created_at, updated_at, [version], eventType, jobClass_id, service_id) 
	SELECT 'ServiceEventEntity', id, created_at, updated_at, [version], eventType, jobClass_id, [service_id]
		FROM service_event;
			</programlisting>
			<para>
				In the new version, all groups have to be connected to a service, in order to be used there.
				All existing groups are not automatically connected, only newly created groups will be. To connect
				the existing groups, visit the Admin menue -> All groups. Click on the button "Add all group flags"
				and watch the logfile from the application server. After all groups are connected, click on the
				button "Fire group change event" and again watch the logfile. The procedure will take some time, 
				depending on the number of groups in the system. After the procedure, there sould be no entry
				in the "service_group_flag" table with the "status" "DITRY". Also you can expect one entry per group
				and group capable service in this table.  
			</para>
			<para>
				Group reconciliation is not done automatically anymore. It is now event driven.
				To get the previous behavior back, follow the instructions in the section
				<command linkend="group_reconciliation">Group Reconciliation</command>.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Update to version 2.4.0</title>
			<para>
				In this version the connection between Federations and IDPs is converted from 1:n to n:m. To reflect this
				change you can drop the column federation_id in the database table idpmetadata, after the new version is deployed.
				Don't forget to delete the foreign key constraint as well.
				You also have to reconnect the idps with their federation. In order to do this, you can poll a federation,
				or wait until this is done automatically. Please also delete unique constraint on the columns entity_id and
				federation_metadata_url on the table federation. These constraints could block your desired configuration
				and are not necessary.
			</para>
			<programlisting language="sql">
ALTER TABLE [idpmetadata]
	DROP COLUMN [federation_id]
			</programlisting>
		</section>		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Configuration</title>
		
		<section>
			<title>SAML Subsystem</title>
			<section>
				<title>Service Provider</title>
				<para>
					The webregistration application needs at least one service provider configured,
					to function. To add such a configuration visit the "SP configuration" Section in 
					the admin menue. Click "Add a configuration". Specify the entity id, private key and
					certificate for this service provider. Click on "save". After the configuration is
					created, you need to edit it. In the textbox "Assertion Consumer Endpoint" you need
					to enter the URL "https://&lt;hostname&gt;/Shibboleth.sso/SAML2/POST". In the textbox
					"ECP Endpoint" the value has to be "https://&lt;hostname&gt;/Shibboleth.sso/SAML2/ECP".
					These values can not be choosen freely for now. This is a planned feature to gain more
					flexibility for the SAML Subsystem. To complete the configuration, add an entry for
					the hostname of the system. You can specify more than one, if virtual hosts are 
					involved. When done, click on save, to persist the changes.
				</para>
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>Federation</title>
				<para>
					The configuration of a single IDP is not supported at the moment. You have
					to configure a federation, even if it consists of only one IDP. 
				</para>
				<para>
					To add a federation, goto the Admin Panel, and click on "Federations". Click on
					"Add Federation" and specify a name of the federation and the URL, where the 
					metadata can be downloaded. Click on save and review the entry, by clicking on 
					the entry at the table of federations. On the view panel for the federation, you 
					can click on "Poll now", to fetch the metadata from the specified URL. 
				</para>
				<para>
					If you want to edit the federation name, or the URL, click on "Edit" on the view panel.
					In the edit panel, you can also specify an "entity category". With this attribute, you can filter
					specific IDPs from your federation metadata. 
				</para>
			</section>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Service</title>
			
			<section>
				<title>Generic Service Properties</title>
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>LDAP Based Services</title>
			</section>			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Business Rules</title>
			
			<section>
				<title>Application Access Rules</title>
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>Service Access Rules</title>
			</section>
			
			<section>
				<title>Group Filtering Rules</title>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>User Management</title>
			<section xml:id="user_reconciliation">
				<title>User Reconciliation</title>
				<para>
					In order to update users when they login, user reconciliation has to be configured. 
					One the "List of job classes" in the admin menue, click on "Create new job class".
					Enter a name (i.e. UserReconciliation) and the job class "edu.kit.scc.webreg.event.UserReconsiliationExecutor".
					Save the entry. Find the entry on the list of job classes, and click on it, to view the 
					item. Use the "edit" link to edit. Use "job on single node" and set two properties: 
					"full_recon" to "false" and "executor" to "web-sso". Save the item.
				</para>
				<para>
					The second step is the connection between the job class and the event. Go to the 
					"User events" item on the admin menue. Choose the job class you created in step one
					and "USER_UPDATE" and click on "add". The change is instantly active, you don't 
					have to save.
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Group Management</title>
			<section xml:id="group_reconciliation">
				<title>Group Reconciliation</title>
				<para>
					In order to update home organization groups when a user logins, group reconciliation has to be configured. 
					One the "List of job classes" in the admin menue, click on "Create new job class".
					Enter a name (i.e. GroupReconciliation) and the job class "edu.kit.scc.webreg.event.GroupReconsiliationExecutor".
					Save the entry. Find the entry on the list of job classes, and click on it, to view the 
					item. Use the "edit" link to edit. Use "job on single node". There are no properties to set.
				</para>
				<para>
					The second step is the connection between the job class and the event. Go to the 
					"Group events" item on the admin menue. Choose the job class you created in step one
					and "GROUP_UPDATE" and click on "add". The change is instantly active, you don't 
					have to save.
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Development</title>
		<para>
			Development of the bwReg application uses Apache Maven as build tool. This tool can be used from the 
			command line or as part of the IDE. At the moment using Eclipse as IDE is recommended 
			for developing.
		</para>
	
		<section>
			<title>Obtaining the source-code</title>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>License</title>
			<para>
				The bwReg Application is released under the GPLv3.
			</para>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Writing Hooks</title>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Writing Tasks</title>
			
		</section>
		
	</chapter>	
	
</book>